<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The search of causes Containing a theophysicall inuestigation of the possiblitie of transmutatorie alchemie. By Timothie Willis, apprentise in phisicke.</title>
            <author>Willis, Timothy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114195</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849423</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849423</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14570</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15486)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14570)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1503:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The search of causes Containing a theophysicall inuestigation of the possiblitie of transmutatorie alchemie. By Timothie Willis, apprentise in phisicke.</title>
                  <author>Willis, Timothy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 87, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alchemy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14570:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14570:1"/>
            <p>THE SEARCH OF CAVSES.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING A THE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophyſicall Inueſtigation of the <hi>Poſsibilitie of Tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie</hi> Alchemie.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Timothie Willis,</hi> Apprentiſe <hi>in Phiſicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by IOHN LEGATT. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14570:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14570:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE cauſe of this Preſſe, is rather compulſory, then voluntary: Indeed an extorted will, proceeding firſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my facility in copies, and thereby from too much liberty in ſome: who of amanuenſed tranſcripts (peraduenture not perfect) gaue mee iust ſuſpition of an ignorant expoſing. Which to preuent, I haue ſent to the worlds view this whatſoeuer, being oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by diſcourſe and arguments at a ſupper betweene diuers learned Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen ſome yeares past. My ſelfe am ſo litle ambitious thereof, that I ſhall thinke it well if it ſcape without taxe, ſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:14570:3"/>virulent: hauing entertained no thought of reply to gainſayers. An incky <hi>Duell</hi> about naturall opinables, ſhould proceed like faults eſcaped in the printing.</p>
            <closer>Mend and ſay nothing.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14570:3"/>
            <head>The ſearch of Cauſes, conteining a Theophyſicall Inueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation <hi>of the poſsibility of Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatorie Alchemie.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE knowledge of trueth reuealed vnto the firſt friends of God, and by ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued vnto vs their children, is more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect then the wiſedome of any Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy. Philoſophers ſeeke for, and require reaſon and neceſſarie cauſes in all things. But we are taught and aſſured, that the beginning was without any ſuch cauſe as they ſeeke after, or wee can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. For nothing is more true, then that all things were made by an infinite
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14570:4"/>power of an incomprehenſible Creator, in that beginning of which we haue no perfect knowledge. And becauſe we are taught that ſo perfect a cauſe can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing not anſwerable to it ſelfe, we muſt beleeue that all his workes be moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in abſolute order of <hi>Number, Weight,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure:</hi> created, made, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, in and vnder an vnchangeable law of created Nature, anſwerable to the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chety pall and chiefe exemplary cauſe of their being and preſeruation. Wherefore to vnderſtand ſo much, as our imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction may comprehend, it is neceſſarie that wee conſider the degrees of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent wiſdome to and in his Creatures, whereby all things are, and continue: And how the eſſentiall cauſes depend and abide inuiolably the ſame, vnto the laſt determination of all time and times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 2.</head>
               <p>BEfore this creation there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this naturall world, eyther in actuall exiſtence, or potentiallie: Neither Forme, Matter; Spirit, Bodie;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14570:4"/>Subſtance, Accident; Time, Place; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Confuſion; Poſitiue, Priuatiue; Abſolute, Relatiue; Abſtract, Concrete; Agent, Patient; Negation, or Affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But one onely the Ineffable and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible <hi>Iah;</hi> diuine Eſſence, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, without beginning or end, whoſe name then was, and in his abſtract Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence euer ſhall be, <hi>I Am.</hi> And ſince the Creation as hee is God the Creator and preſeruer, &amp;c. <hi>Emanuel,</hi> God with vs, which <hi>Vs</hi> is man, conteining in him ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what by proportion from the Sonne of God and man, and from Angels, to the inſenſible Center of the earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 3.</head>
               <p>THe difference or diſtance betweene Being and abſolute not being, is infinite: And therefore cannot be medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, or filled, but by an infinite Power: But there is nothing infinite in Power, ſauing onely the vncreated Power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out beginning or ending. Of whoſe counſels we may not require cauſe or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe they exceed reaſon, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14570:5"/>by vs be comprehended. This power becauſe it is infinite, is alwaies the ſame without change. Wherefore it is ſimply without reſpect or relation <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe:</hi> from which all created <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> commeth, and on it depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. And this created <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Goodnes</hi> to it ſelfe and euery particular creature is reſpectiue and relatiue. The firſt abſolute Power infinite, and infinitely Good, with his will eternally decreed a creation: and with his infinite action and ſpirit effected the ſame: Infinite in the Creator, though determined and finite in the Creature, <hi>Ad modum Recipientis.</hi> So we finde in this workmanſhip of the Almighty three cauſes, which are a rule, intellectual and ideall law, in and to the creature: <hi>Power, Will, Spirit,</hi> being three coeſſential in one God, and three diſtinct in the Creature concerning his operations, though one in the vniuerſality of their ſubiect, much more in the cauſe whereon they depend. For what Creature ſoeuer ſhall doe any thing, muſt haue Power to effect, Will to work, and inſtruments of action; which is Spirit, giuing motion: and this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14570:5"/>to all creatures, vnder what degree of ſubſtance ſoeuer they bee particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zied. For the Philoſophers power meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſiue, concerneth only a ſuppoſition of naturall diſpoſition and appetite to a proceſſe, <hi>A non Ente tali ad ens tale.</hi> But except they will imagine it to bee with priuation of action in the patible or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ſubiect (which is abſurd) they muſt needs grant this power to effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 4.</head>
               <p>IN the hiſtory of the Creation we finde thus. In the beginning God made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, &amp;c. as there followeth. Where note, that the word <hi>Deep, Abyſſus,</hi> or <hi>Chaos,</hi> was that which is heere called heauen and earth, being yet one confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed heape or maſſe, vndiuided, without forme, &amp; void, oueruailed with vniuerſal darknes; which darknes was not the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of light, becauſe no created or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue light had then bin.
<note place="margin">2. Eſdras, 6.39.</note> But without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny voice the darkneſſe was on euery ſide with ſilence. From this matter, Time and Place only beginneth the ſearch of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14570:6"/>vnderſtanding, and created wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, vnto which all Philoſophy in the higheſt Metaphyſicks muſt be reduced. For no reaſon can be giuen, or inueſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of that which was not: And not any thing euer was, but in ſome time and place: which haue no vſe but onely to meaſure and conteine. But before this beginning their neither was meaſure nor thing meaſured; Conteiner nor thing conteined: And therefore no time, no place: But both had being and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in and with this creation, beeing themſelues creatures, and concluded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law of Nature: which here in this <hi>Reſhith</hi> with them tooke beginning. I am not ignorant, that a late writer labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth much about <hi>Principium increatum.</hi> In which he would haue this darke and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent mother, the common wombe, this Chaos of poſſibilities, this all changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnformed to bee and receiue begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; or more explicately to be with it Coaeuall. But that is too Chaldaicall, and implieth an eternitie and infinite forebeing of Matter, Time, and Place: which agreeth not with the infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14570:6"/>and contradictorie predicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Deus,</hi> and <hi>Non Deus.</hi> And there is nothing definible, demonſtrable, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent out of any principle of naturall wiſedome, which this beginning of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Time, and Place doe not as certainly auerre, as the ſuppoſed eternity of them. Beſides that it is more orthodoxall: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his phraſe and ſentence can beare conſtruction of that <hi>Word</hi> which was in and from the beginning; by which all things were made: And receiue the conſtruction of Saint <hi>Paulsſermon</hi> to the Athenians. Now therefore let vs ſee what riuers run from this ſea, Conducts from this wellhead: and what principles of Philoſophie wee are neceſſarily tyed vnto by this moſt certaine and true beginning of nature and naturall cauſes. No doubt whatſoeuer is elſewhere ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily or probably deliuered, is either directly taken from hence, Or elſe is but a ſhadow of this ſubſtance, and a deriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 5.</head>
               <p>EVerie worke and action of God, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed or implied in his Creation,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14570:7"/>hath as a neceſſary cauſe produced ſome created effect, and eſtabliſhed it vnder the law of Nature, with time ſtill to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. By his Power in the beginning he created that voide and vnformed <hi>Chaos,</hi> which becauſe it was void &amp; vnformed, had power and hability alike to euerie thing or forme. And becauſe nature, that is the Creature, is the Image of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, as being Relatiue to him; There is in it a naturall will and appetite vnto perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which is the naturall <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of euery creature, which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by diſtinction, in inſtruments, parts, &amp;c. That the heauens may declare the glory of God, and all his works mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his holy name. The third cauſe in the creature was yet wanting; that is, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the formall cauſe of motion, in euery Creature: which likewiſe anſwered his proper cauſe, diſtinct from the other, as is ſaid in their effects relatiuely, but not in their vniuerſall ſubiect, nor in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totypal being,</hi> whoſe Image they are: Three in One, and One in Three, or rather Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Coeſſentiall in Vnity, and Vnity in Trinity. The ſpirit of God moued vpon the waters. The ſpirit mouing vpon the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14570:7"/>waters created in them ſpiritualneſſe and naturall motion, in ſuch proportion as might moſt abſolutely anſwer the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Creators diſpoſition, and harmony in the innumerable variety of all his particular creatures: and be a moſt ſure ground to informe the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of reaſon by exact dependence of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects vpon their cauſes. The whole <hi>Chaos</hi> conteined two parts, Water and Earth. In this there is diuerſity of poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aboue and beneath. The Water was aboue the Earth, &amp; therfore lighter and more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of actiuity; The Earth was vnder the waters, and therfore heauier &amp; naturally more paſſible. The ſpirit mooued vpon the ſurface of the waters, which then thereby became more ſpirituall, actiue, &amp; ſtirring: &amp; from thence the other waters in that deepe receiued their dower in the like vertues in proportion, euen to thoſe that were contiguall to the earth. The Earth in it ſelfe hath no power of ſpirit or motion, but mediatly by the Waters: and that likewiſe in exact and graduated proportion, ſufficient for the agreeing diuerſity of al bodies. This ſpiritualnes or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14570:8"/>naturall ſpirit being but potentially in the waters, could not in naturall courſe (which God had now eſtabliſhed) be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but by a meane. The Spirit was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, Motion breeds heat, Heate cauſeth rarefaction, or ſubtilty: &amp; ſubtilty is the perfection of ſpirit in euerie kind: And of all ſpirituall things light is moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, which therefore was the firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture actually diſtinguiſhed in and out of the confuſed Chaos. And that which before was the confuſed power of all things, void, and without forme, by this appeared the vniuerſall matter of all bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, informed with light, the moſt vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall of all formes. And as in the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe nature trauailed with the burthen of this wonderfull birth in her wombe, and as it were ſate hatching her egges, ſo now in this light ſhee was deliuered of her firſt borne: and after diſcloſed her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chickens, formed and well ſhaped, out of the ſhell of darkeneſſe. And here the waters were endowed with Spirit, Motion, Heat, and Light, as is aforeſaid: which light was not actually in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour waters (as nights Mantle proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth:)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14570:8"/>But ſhewing the neereneſſe of water vnto light by tranſparence, the eaſie reception of light, their eaſie rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction by the worke of heate, the child of Spirit, doe giue good teſtimony of lights materiality. But this is not ſo proper to the vniuerſall light, of which we ſpeake, by which the ſuperiour waters bee continually illumined and illuſtred, without any ſhadow of the night of our leſſe generall time; yet it may ſerue in neere ſimilitude to illuſtrate. The next diſtinct Creature named the <hi>Expanſion,</hi> Firmament, or Heauen (which a certaine Wiſeman calleth the heauenly <hi>Ayre</hi>) had in the very inſtant of his calling and creation an office appointed moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: To diuide the waters aboue from the waters below. And heere is no mention made of Ayre and Fire, but of Motion and Light, which are neuer without heate, the moſt proper paſſion or forme of that which wee commonlie call Fire: Alſo of the vpper Waters and their rarefaction, which agreeth with the Ayre of common Philoſophie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14570:9"/>in the efficient and ſubiect. But whether thoſe names be proper or no, concerneth not this place: and I haue elſewhere paradoxally handled. Of the ſubſtance &amp; compoſition of heauen many heads haue brought forth many hornes: and arming their reaſons with fantaſticall imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, haue puſhed at each other ſo long till they be all galled. It is ſufficient for vs to conſider their vſe and office: that is, to deuide the waters aboue from the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters below; and how being compoſed of the common <hi>Chaos,</hi> water and earth, more pure then things beneath them, leſſe pure then things aboue them, they be ſolid, fixed, permanent, and as it were of an immortall ſubſtance, patible onely by fire.
<note place="margin">Iob 37.18.</note> And therefore it is ſaid, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens are ſtrong and as a molten glaſſe. For when the Spirit getteth the vpper hand in a pure and cleane body, and that bodie afterwards of the Spirit in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coniunction, not by incraſſation of the ſpirit but by ſubtilation of the body, the whole compound becommeth quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſentiall: then all is permanent, and, as you would ſay, fixed ſpiritually. Then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14570:9"/>there is no naturall alteration nor cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. I know that ſome writers make two diſtinct materialities, or <hi>materias pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> firſt matters in this beginning of creation: one containing the water of heauen aboue, the other a confuſed maſſe of earth and water, the corporalitie of all ſublunarie bodies. But that opinion ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to draw a tayle after it of many ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniences: &amp; that golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chaine of <hi>Participation of Symboles,</hi> which linketh heauen and earth together, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide two materiall principles of one creature. Neither can ſuch duality ſubſiſt with that <hi>Talmudique</hi> myſterie of light ſhining out of darkenes, which is figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely <hi>verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei in nobis.</hi> Then there is no naturall alteration nor corruption, but <hi>mens ſana in corpore ſano,</hi> a pure ſpirit in a perfect bodie. Next after the firmament and this diuiſion of waters, followed the ſeparation or parting of the waters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the firmament from the earth; whereby ſea and land were made. In all this relation and reſpect are manifeſt; darkeneſſe and light aboue, beneath; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14570:10"/>diuider, or meane betweene extreames, Water, Earth, Sea, Land; wet, dry, Motion, Reſt, &amp;c. Then in order fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, In the earth Vegetables, In heauen ſtarres and their offices, In the waters Fiſh and Foule: In the earth againe ſenſibles, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Brutes, or Irrationals: Laſtly Man with appointment of meate for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and all ſenſibles, except fiſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 6.</head>
               <p>IN the beginning the Waters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined all; were conteined of none, but teemed in darkeneſſe. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens were of olde; And the earth that was of the water, by the Word of God. VVherefore the world that then was, periſhed by water. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and earth which now are, bee kept in ſtore by the ſame Word vnto fire. The firſt matter of all things is water: and therefore the firſt clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14570:10"/>is by and with water. The laſt perfection of all things is ſpirit, and the laſt cleanſing is by fire, which is the violence of the ſpirit conſuming all matter imperfectible, and leauing in an immortall bodie, that which is pure, cleane, and perfectible. In which triumph of the ſpirit all ſhall burne ſauing the perfect ſeede of them that ſcaped in the waters.</p>
               <p>For nothing that is vncleane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the laſt and ſecond perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fire, not hauing beene wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and depured in the firſt of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But how the earth was of water, whether by ſeparation of the lower waters when the drie land appeared, or by ſubſidence of the heauier part of the Chaos in the rarefaction cauſed by the ſpirit moouing, is a matter of great and neceſſarie conſequence: doubtleſſe it was by both, as wee ſee in depuring of liquors and Chymicall extractions. And ſo the ſecond world is of the diuiding of fire, as in ſpagiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call myſteries wee may plainelie ſee.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14570:11"/>This is true in that we ſeeke after: which is more eaſie to vnderſtand if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the forme, or eſſentially inſeparable from the forme of fire, was made by the ſpirits mouing vpon the waters, and that the life and fewell of fire is aer. The waters as being moſt ſpiritual had the firſt ornament of diſtinction and forme in all degrees: firſt light (which ſome thinke to comprehend Angels) and therefore fire. But that thought hath many great aduerſaries, and may imply matter of ſtrong hereſye, as though they had beene Coadiutors, or agents in the following dayes of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore they doe beſt which vnderſtand the creation of Angels to be in the ſixt day, in which man himſelfe alſo was created: beſides many other ſound reaſons. Then heauen followed the diuider and mediator of the waters aboue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beneath: next vegetables, &amp;c. as before: where note that before any ſenſible creature was created in the water or earth, the better part, that is, the ſuperior waters, and the heauen, had
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14570:11"/>all their furniture of light, with the whole hoaſt of heauen, of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtarres and their offices. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Angels a little before man. For though it bee not defined when An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels were created; yet their reſidence beeing in heauen, and their Indiuidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie immortall, it cannot bee doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they were before and neere the perfecteſt forme of the ruling crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And the light of Angels in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigination muſt differ infinitely from the inacceſſible light of God. And as they could not ſuffer by water, ſo they that continued in their originall light ſhall not periſh nor ſuffer by fire, as all other things ſhall, euen the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens themſelues. The heauens and earth which are kept by the ſame word in ſtore, and reſerued vnto fire, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. Pſa. 102.25</note> Thou haſt layed the foundations of the earth, the heauens are the worke of thine hands, they ſhall periſh but thou ſhalt endure: Euen they all ſhall waxe olde as doth a garment, as a veſture ſhalt thou change them, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14570:12"/>they ſhall bee changed,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.12. Eccl. 17.31.</note> &amp;c. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens beeing on fire ſhall bee diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and the Elements ſhall melt with heate, &amp;c. VVhat is more cleere then the Sunne? yet it ſhall faile; Yea the heauens and ſtarres though inſenſible bee farre more excellent then the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible creatures of the earth, and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour waters: Not concerning their forme, but concerning their compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, perfect mixture, and pure mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of corporalitie: All which cauſe their permanent indiuidualitie. Such is the ſubſtance of our queſtion. The ſtarres are vncleane in his ſight: How much more man euen the Sonne of man,
<note place="margin">Iob 15.15.</note> which is but a worme? &amp;c. The heauens are not cleane in his ſight, how much more Man? For man is of the earth. And heauen is the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of waters: In which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fixed &amp; permanent, which cannot bee without the action of their ſpirit of light and fire. For though euerie one haue their part of all foure: Yet wee finde the earth and ayre patible, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14570:12"/>as it were Nurſes or rather Seminaries, and very wombes of corruption, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and death: From which (not ſpeaking of them in their regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bodies,) no ſacrament either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine or naturall is taken: And in, from, and by which all things both macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſmicall and microcoſmicall haue their Morbificall exhalations. But the other two, water, and fire, bee the cleanſers and naturall renewers of all; which as they decay not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſo doe they preſerue. For the fiſhes were not brought into the Arke, but were preſerued in their own proper Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And by the way we may obſerue one notable doctrine. That the more pure, cleane, and ſubtile any thing is in the materialitie of his primitiue nature, the more irreuocable is the ruine and deſtruction, if it ſuffer vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence aboue or beyond that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, waight, and meaſure in which it was created. So wee ſee the fall of Angels eternally iudged, and vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſubſtance bee irreducible. And this in naturall things &amp; naturall cauſes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14570:13"/>is alſo true. But to proceede: after in the creation of ſenſible creatures the waters were firſt ſerued with fiſh &amp; ſoules, which are attributed and appropriated vnto the waters, becauſe ayre commeth by rarefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of waters, and is extended vnder the hollow of heauen. Laſtly was Man, being the <hi>Epitome</hi> and Abridgement of the whole Creation; and therfore right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Microcoſmus,</hi> a little world: for whoſe vſe and ſeruice all other things were created: For the good or bad vſe whereof, he ſhall account to his and their Creator <hi>God Almighty.</hi> The order of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding heerein, we ſee to be from the moſt ſimple and vniuerſall, to the moſt compound and ſpeciall or particular. So ſenſibles are more compounded then ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, Man more then other ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; minerals leſſe then vegetables: and all concerning their materiality, of the firſt Chaos, partakers of the eſſentiall corporality, which conteined all in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 7.</head>
               <p>IN this Chronicle of the creation, there is very excellently taught the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14570:13"/>of all Creatures, their compoſition, and ſtate of their naturall life. There are two corporal or bodied Elements, Earth and Water; of which all things vnder heauen are materially compounded: The ſpirit of life in euery thing is his naturall heate, ioyned therewith by the meanes of the ayre (which is here called the rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied waters,) firſt created by the motion of the ſpirit, and made able to multiply it ſelfe in any fit and prepared ſubiect. This heate is chiefly in the light, which was firſt brought out of the Chaos, and dwelleth in the rarefied waters, as in their proper ſubiect. So the whole compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſteth of foure; two patient and materiall reſpectiuely, inferior water and earth: two agent and formall reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuperior water and heate, or light: which if we call ayre and fire in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, it ſhall be indifferent, for it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not what names or words be vſed, ſo the thing be vnderſtood. Theſe foure E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements or parts of compoſition muſt be conſidered two waies; particularly, and generally. Conſidered particularly they euer concurre to the compoſition of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14570:14"/>things corruptible: but generally, of things incorruptible. To which purpoſe let vs conſider; that there is a generall light, made before the heauens: of and with which the Elements, and euery e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementary compound doth communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate more or leſſe: and thereby hath in it ſome ſparke of incorruptibility, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility to attaine it, according to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue natural predeſtination of his firſt creation; which alſo it might, and ſhould enioy, were it adapted to fit digeſtion, and fermentation of it ſelfe: where all the Elements ſhould neuer ceaſe from their circular labour vntill by equall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and temper that ſubiect could no more be altered; of which there is ſome neere example in Gold and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a generall Heauen, not made to diſtinguiſh times and ſeaſons, but to diuide, and to bee as it were a Land-marke betweene the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, (the interpretations of the Hebrew <hi>Maim,</hi> and the Comments of the Aerial Expanſion may haue their truth, not oppoſing this diuiſor:) which generall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14570:14"/>heauen giueth generall influence from the Waters aboue, by meanes of the generall light, into the inferiour Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and elementarie compounds, and alſo ſpirituall fixation: continuing and preſeruing the cauſe of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptibilitie, beeing an actiue Spirit of life, able to worke by digeſtion and fermentation as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a generall and vniuerſall Time, and that of diuers degrees. When the Chaos was created, Time was created with it. And as the matter of all things, being then in this Chaos, is incorruptible in it ſelfe, though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſlie paſſible in his indefiniteneſſe to all formes: ſo is that time with it crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in it ſelfe abſtractiuely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, vndiuided, though communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto Elements and Compounds, and meaſuring in them no other thing then the incorruptibility of their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Beſides this, there is another ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Time, meaſuring the generall and incorruptible matter, which ſlept in vnreuealed darkneſſe. And as the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14570:15"/>firſt meaſureth in the Elements and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental bodies the incorruptibility of the matter, ſo this meaſureth in them the ſame of their formes, to the preſeruation of one generall forme in one generall matter of naturall tranſcendence. The third generall Time began with the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament; which time meaſureth the third order of naturall Being from the Chaos; and the ſecond order of diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the generall light. That is the diuiſion of waters, and therefore it is in the firſt degree of compoſition, alterable by generation and corruption: for in it the foure elements were perfected of all naturall ſublunary things. This time is the firſt of all, vnto which our ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reacheth, concerning the naturall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of things corruptible and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: for the other two come neerer the laſt diſſolution, when al things ſhal ſtand adorned in one light, or fall confuſed in one darkneſſe. And theſe vniuerſall and incorruptible cauſes, Matter and Forme, are really according to their natures in the elements and euery compound; and either ſhall with them in their preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14570:15"/>continue vnto the laſt poſſibility of their predeſtination, or alter them that they may ſo continue; or elſe being ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from them returne to their proper place, vnder the commenſuration of their proper time, till all things be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the incorruptible regeneration of an immortall ſpring. So is their particular matter and forme ſeparable, corruptible in reſpect of the compoſition; and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by particular times, in which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations and corruptions do happen of all things thereunto ſubiect. The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular light began with the Starres, and that of ſo many different effects, as there be varieties in their motion, receptions of light, irradiations, and whatſoeuer elſe in true Aſtronomy can bee ſaid of them. This is the particular beginning of time and times, and the proper mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all ſpecifications and particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: Yet ſome would haue the meaſure of ſpecifications to be in the time of the vnſtarred heauens, and of particularities as is here ſaid. It is no inconuenience to agree with them, both haue their ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, but agree in the iſſue of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14570:16"/>If it be obiected, that this being true, vegetables be incorruptible, becauſe they were created before this light, and time of the Stars; I ſay, it followeth not. For they are made of earth and inferiour waters, earth being predominant, which imply matter and forme ſeparable, and by conſequent corruptibility of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pound, not withſtanding the concours of the other two elements aforeſaid. They were giuen for food to man, and all other animals (except Fiſhes) which were made after the Stars; and therefore doe communicate in nature with them. And though they were made before the light and time of generations and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, yet they were not then abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely perfect. For neither had they then increaſed their ſpecies with ſucceſſion of indiuiduals, nor attained their laſt end in which al perfection is conſummate: that is, to be meate for man and beaſts, made in the light and times of generations. But therein we may note, that all things made before this time, being generable and corruptible, be in their generations hermaphroditicall: and therein differ
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14570:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the other more multitudinary and angulare. And from this place a good cabaliſt may gather ſomething of the immortalitie of the fleſh, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of reſurrection: becauſe their foode is of that which in the firſt creation concerning time and light, is incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; amongſt which there is a tree of life. What then ſhall we ſay of meate and medicine made of that, which in creation preceeds theſe, in his particular bodie is durable with the heauens, leſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and angulare then any vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But to returne: moreouer the earth and all things therein receiued the curſe, and became hereunto ſubiect by <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and cannot without ſweate and labour eate their bread, that is, enioy the predeſtination of the ſpirit of life which is in them. But if they were helped and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by ſome matter like and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall to that ſpirit of life, which they haue of the vniuerſall light, and the vpper waters meaſured by the vniuerſall time of the vnſtarred hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; noe doubt they might endure
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14570:17"/>farre beyond that time they now doe, if peraduenture not to the worlds ende: which in their preſent eſtate is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for many cauſes, and by reaſon here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditarie corruption hath taken ſo great and deepe roote; as one (though to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other end) ſaith;
<q>
                     <l>Damnoſa quid non imminuit Dies?</l>
                     <l>Aetas Parentum, peior auis tulit</l>
                     <l>Nos nequiores, mox daturos</l>
                     <l>Progeniem vitioſiorem.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Wherein the whole world, and euerie part thereof, haue their part, both in quantity diminiſhed, life ſhortned, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vertues decayed, and generally in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority of all things that belong to their naturall being or well being: and ſhall not be reſtored, vntill the general reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the vniuerſe. Say vnto a woman which trauaileth,
<note place="margin">2. Efdras. 5.52.</note> wherefore are not they whom thou haſt now brought forth like thoſe that were before thee, but leſſe of ſtature? And ſhe will anſwer thee, ſome were born in the flower of youth, others were borne in the time of age, when the wombe failed: Conſider now that yee are leſſe of ſtature then thoſe that were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14570:17"/>before you, and ſo are they that come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you leſſe then they: as the Creatures which now beginne to be old, and haue paſſed ouer the ſtrength of youth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 8.</head>
               <p>OF theſe two kinds of eſſentiall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, generall and particular, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible and incorruptible, all ſublunary things conſiſt and haue their being and exiſtence in matter and forme, body and ſpirit. And are in poſſibility to ſuch end, as naturally follow theſe beginnings, corruptible or incorruptible, tranſumta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or permanent. And nature naturally proceeding, euer intendeth the greateſt naturall perfection in all her workes, and the preſeruation thereof. But becauſe in the excellent ornament and beauty of Gods glorious workmanſhip (conſiſting of innumerable variety of ſeuerall ſpecies and perticularities in nature) all partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate not alike, of the incorruptible cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nor be alike tempered by the digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their compounding Elements, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things of neceſſity are of ſhorter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14570:18"/>then other, more ſubiect to change and corruption. This change &amp; corruption, being properly the death of euery particular body, commeth not by vtter deſtruction or annihilation of any eſſential part, but is only a diſorganizing of the ſpirits tenement, and a ſeparating of theſe ſaid parts, each returning to his place vnder the meaſure of generall time. Neither do any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo periſh, but that their mortall immortalitie, vnder the ſaid comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuration continuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlds end, is manifeſt. For thoſe things, which in their indiuiduall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies haue not this immortality (as wee ſee the heauens, gold, &amp; precious ſtones to haue) are preſerued here by ſucceſſion, as it were of immortall ſeede. For all men came out of <hi>Adams</hi> loynes: And his ſubſtance by propagation continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the laſt end of al natural things. In contemplation wherof the Greek Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers affirme, that in all ſeedes there is ſomthing wonderful, proportionable to the Element of Stars. But if we conſider the regeneration of this body in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, purified Elements, though it be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14570:18"/>aboue the compaſſe of common reaſon, and ſeeme miraculous; yet no doubt wee may therein contemplate, and moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably diſcerne the complement of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the immortality of euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, which before was ſhadowed in ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion. <hi>Nothing can proceede infinitely in change;</hi> therefore there muſt bee ſome end or period of particular times, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in changes happen. <hi>The whole memorie of Nature, being the Image of God, cannot bee blotted out and destroyed.</hi> Therefore after the determination of number, to auoide infinitie, there ſhall be an immortality of particular things: Not by the ruine of Nature, but by the full acted accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the whole poſsibility, and ſatisfying the appetite of all cauſes. If it bee demaunded whether this ſhall alſo bee in other ſenſibles, vegetables, and minerals, the anſwer requires modeſtie, for it is not made certaine vnto vs; <hi>Et praestat dubitare de occultis, quàm liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare de incertis.</hi> For my ſelfe I rather thinke of the Negatiue. My reaſon is: The whole vniuerſitie and frame of the creation is the Image of God: And this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14570:19"/>whatſoeuer is epitomized in Man, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining moſt exactly the whole harmony and diſcord, order and confuſion of all cauſes and effects, according as he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth or falleth to God his maſter. And ſo is the true and real ſtorehouſe of al Gods workes, and his moſt perfect Image: the Image of his glorie if hee ſtand, of his wrath and iudgement if he fall. Alt hings were bleſſed for his ſake &amp; vſe: the ſame were curſed for his ſinne and abuſing the creatures contrary to commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: hee ſhall account to God as his Steward for all; and in him they ſhall be perfected to immortality, not diſtinctlie in their preſent ſhapes, but as hauing in him that they are. For after the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration man hath no more vſe of them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary or ornamentall. And ſo the cauſe of their natural and diſtinct be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ceaſeth. So the whole creature is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, that is, the generall cauſes of matter and forme, of which all things were in an elementall body perfectly tryed, digeſted, depured, &amp; inſeparably vnited, and as it were fixed in the higheſt perfection, which is Man. In whom all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14570:19"/>naturall bodies of which weſpeake, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre and reſt, as al riuers run into the ſea making one deepe. And if the expoſition of <hi>Dionyſius Carthuſianus</hi> be not receiued, peraduenture this may agree with the meaning of S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 8. Cha. to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> from the 19. verſe to the 24. To this purpoſe we may further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, how God in all his workes euer abhorred mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude tending to diuiſion, making all things conſpire in vnity of moſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed perfection. In the creation of the ſecond day it is not ſaid, And God ſaw that it was good. Not that the Creatures of that day wanted his bleſſing, but to teach vs the danger of diuiſion, which beginning in the firſt defection from v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, endeth in confuſion: and is neuer reſtored but by returning againe from the tumult of multiplied duality, and conſpiring in the vnited goodneſſe of all good things, to receiue the vndiuided bleſſing of reſt and quietneſſe in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Septenarie. So God ſaw all that he had made, and loe it was very good. It is not ſaid, he ſaw them and euerie of them, and they were good. <hi>Duo,</hi> two, as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14570:20"/>the number of diuiſion had no bleſſing, but in 6. being vnitiuely tripled, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the firſt vniuerſall cauſes, it was ioyned to the number of all, as one of, in, and with them, without diuiſion for them; and ſo reſted in the perfection of vnity, ſanctifying the creature in 7. And as all things natural are of three vniuerſal cauſes, ſo on that roote is ſquared the laſt preparation of them, which is Man: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing perfection in 10. by which, 9. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth into vnity, the firſt and laſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all perfections. For 6. and 9. be the numbers of preparation and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 7. and 10. the numbers of reſt and perfection in nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 9.</head>
               <p>NOW let vs enquire whither it bee poſſible in nature to produce ſuch a compounded ſubſtance, tempered of the Elements, in which, after exact digeſtion, the predominancy of the ſpiritual cauſes ſhall be manifeſted in true figure of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. So that the appetite of this matter being fully ſatisfied, it ſhall bee capable of no greater natural perfection, nor ſubiect to change in it ſelfe: but, like
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14570:20"/>the ſuperior waters, mixe it ſelfe with the ſpirit of life in euery natural thing, &amp; work in it reſtauration &amp; preſeruation in ſuch meaſure, as the naturall predeſtination of that thing wherwith it is ioined is able to receiue: and ſo be <hi>Genus generum,</hi> and <hi>forma formarum,</hi> moſt vniuerſall to all ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentate compounds. I ſay a naturall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and naturall change, meaning ſo great and high degree, as the poſſibility of this world, haſting in ſpeedy fluxe to an end, can ſuffer and beare. For I know that when the pure heauens, and perfect elements doe burne, melt, and ſhall bee purged with the powerfull fire in the laſt complement of Nature, that then alſo all things of or vnder them conſiſting, ſhall much more ſuffer the ſame. Such things therefore as we ſpeake of be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly diuided into animals, vegetables, and minerals: vnderſtanding each largely to comprehend all the particular <hi>Species</hi> of their owne kind, alſo all errors whether by abundance or defect of matter, ſtrength and weaknes of cauſes, &amp;c. amongſt theſe we alſo comprehend <hi>lithophytes,</hi> tranſplanted from a vegetable roote to a minerall body, and <hi>zoophytes,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14570:21"/>which for the moſt part haue in neereſt agreement an animall body, and a mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall houſe. For a ground and principle heerein we aſſume that which with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent is receiued in euery ſect of Philoſophy: <hi>Nature not hindered in her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions doth produce that wherein ſhe laboureth, in the greatest perfection that may be.</hi> This we ſee to be true in all indiuiduall things, in the ſpecification of their birthes, in their proper and naturall matrices: as alſo in vnnaturall iſſues from vnproper and vnnaturall matrices: and in Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of ſuperfluity, defect, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In all which nature frameth ſomthing as neere to the ſpecifical perfection of the ſeede ſowen, as the matrice, matter, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and adaptation thereof will ſuffer: Alſo in equiuocall generations, &amp; things animated by fermentation, putrifaction, &amp;c. And this alſo in Vegetables, as in graffing; where a Crab-ſtocke feedeth a Pippin. In tranſplantation, as of wheate into Rye, &amp;c. In culture, both of degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and exaltation, as in garden fruits, double flowers, &amp;c. Likewiſe in minerals, as is ſufficiently declared by good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14570:21"/>and daily experienced by ſuch as vſe iudgement in ſearching, digging, and vſe of Mines. Alſo in ſpagyricall matura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vnripe Mines, and of vnperfect minerals by cohobating imbibition of fit minerall waters, &amp;c. The ſecond ſeruing to this point, is no leſſe euident and common. <hi>Euerie effect is the effect of ſome cauſe, and therefore anſwerable vnto it.</hi> And of this followeth a third. <hi>There is no reall cauſe actually being, without his effect in actus all exiſtence:</hi> Elſe ſhould nature labour in vaine, and conſume her ſelfe about no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with leſſe profit, then a mountaine calling a Midwife to bee deliuered of a Mouſe. This being graunted, let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what is before prooued of the difference of cauſes, <hi>Generall</hi> and <hi>Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,</hi> not taking away the ſubalternate dependence of all, for the whole beeing of ſubiects with their inherent vertues and applications, as they now are to themſelues and others. By particular I meane not indiuiduall, but that which is put vnder or beneath the vniuerſality of Natures indefiniteneſſe, by being appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to any inferior or ſubalternate
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14570:22"/>kind of ſpecificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. General cauſes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in themſelues produce generall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, but receiued in particular ſubiects work according to euery particular kind, in Animals, Vegetables, and Minerals. This barre or repulſion from generality commeth by ſpecification; and ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation from the concourſe of particular cauſes, hindering nature from her gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall worke. The matter is indifferent to all; becauſe it is generall, and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible: and deſiring a forme moſt naturall to it ſelfe, muſt needs be beſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with generality. Take away the particular ſpecificating cauſes, and this generall effect muſt needs follow: as the light of the Sunne is altered according to the colour of any Glaſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through it paſſeth, which glaſſe being taken away, it appeareth in that generall brightneſſe which is proper to it ſelfe. If therefore it bee poſſible to continue in nature the action of the generall cauſes not hindered by ſubalternation of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularity, vnto the laſt digeſtiue fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this matter, no doubt there wil be produced an effect generall, a reall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſting
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14570:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubſtance, indefinite, indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, to al ſpecificated ſubſtances: being ſpirit of naturall life in all perfection to euery one in his kind, of which it ſhall be receiued as aforeſaid. As the honour and authority of a King, continuing in his owne abſolute power vndiminiſhed, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth honour and authoritie to all kinde of his ſubiects to euery one according to his place, degree, and office. And to his ſubiects is as it were <hi>Genus generum,</hi> and <hi>Forma formarum:</hi> ſo matter beeing in it ſelfe indifferent to all, and informed in the firſt light of Nature, with the moſt vniuerſall forme of ſimplicitie, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition naturally deſireth the moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall forme which is poſsible for any elementate compound to haue. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is ſpecificated according to the ſubalternate cauſes working there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. As we may ſay, a King in his officers is coarcted into a Chancellor, a Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, an Admirall, Iudge, Iuſtice, Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 10.</head>
               <p>THe poſsibility of this general vnſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificated ſubſtance appeareth: and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14570:23"/>more, a very neceſsity thereof, leſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould worke in vaine, hauing the concourſe of all neceſſary cauſes not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. Let vs therefore ſearch further, how and of what this may bee done, in any ſublunary matter compounded of the elements, animall, vegetable, mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, largely taken as aforeſaid. Firſt let vs conſider the ſtate of innocency, in which all things were abſolutely perfect, each in his owne kinde: ſo that the meaſure of the generall cauſes in them was not hindered from their actions by any ſeed of corruption or clog of groſſeneſſe, but free in their owne libertie to worke and produce effects anſwerable to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in euery body. For all bodies in their naturall being are not alike perdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but graduated with more or leſſe, as the concourſe of particular cauſes and agents is more or leſſe in them. And thoſe, whoſe compoſition is moſt ſimple and leaſt remote from the Elements by ſubalternation, are of all others leaſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to corruption in their ſpecificated naturall bodies: as minerals. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne where we left; this primitiue and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14570:23"/>genethliacal perfection by <hi>Adams</hi> fal was impaired and ouerueiled, as it were in a ſhadow of death: ſo that thoſe things which God ſaw to be good, were now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the fruite and iuyce of that tree in which the knowledge of euill grew: and being poyſoned by <hi>Adams</hi> taſte, were with him curſed. Neither was there any way left for him to enioy their goodneſſe ſeuered from euill, but by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and trauaile. Curſed is the earth for thy ſake. In ſorrow ſhalt thou eate of it all the daies of thy life. In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eate thy bread, vntill thou returne to earth. This ſweate and trauell to eate bread is not tyed to the table of meales, nor to plowing and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but is generall to the fruition of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry naturall thing in his vſe of vertue and goodneſſe. Was not the water made ſweete with wood,
<note place="margin">Ecclus. 38.</note> that men might know the vertue thereof? The vertue of this wood and all other things was knowne to <hi>Adam,</hi> but loſt in the heires of the ſlothfull, married vnto the beauty of the Daughters of men, either refuſing, or not rightly vnderſtanding the ſweate of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14570:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>bread. Man became rebellious and diſobedient vnto God; ſo other creatures to man. Man is reſtored to God by the ſuffering of one moſt perfect; ſo naturall things vnder the ordinance of God, vnto man by one moſt exactly purified, dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted &amp; regenerated naturall compound. And (not defining) I thinke it no error to ſay,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. 8.</note> that as euery creature is ſubiect to vanitie, and groneth with vs, and at laſt ſhall be deliuered from the bondage of corruption vnto the glorious libertie of the ſonnes of God: ſo alſo there may be naturally, before that conſummation of all things, ſome proofe of this reſtored incorruptibilitie, really exiſting in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete elementate Compound, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid in the 9. chapter. Of this matter and ſubſtance ſpeaketh <hi>Roger Bacon.</hi> It is poſſible to nature and art helping nature, to prepare <hi>Corpus aequalis complexionis, in quo omnia elementa ſunt aequalia, &amp; adaequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, quo-ad virtutes. Neceſſe etiam eſt quòd ſit poſſibilitas huius corporis; quoniam corpora in reſurrectione non poſſunt habere incorruptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; immortalitatem, niſi per hoc corpus &amp;c.</hi> and in another place, <hi>Et hoc eſt corpus
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14570:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>aequale, ex quo componentur corpora poſt reſurrectionem.</hi> And this is the reſt from ſweat and labour that euery naturall thing ſhall haue after it is returned into earth; in the ſecond purifying of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination by fire: As our <hi>Hermes</hi> ſaith of the worlds wonder, <hi>Vis eius eſt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra, ſi verſa fuerit in terram.</hi> The perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the earthly paradiſe decaied not: but the way thereof was precluded: whither nature cannot enter, but by paſſing the fiery ſword. Man in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is called <hi>Omnis creatura,</hi> euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: And therefore in him ſhall this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring from groning and trauailing, and deliuerie from the bondage of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee <hi>vltimatè,</hi> in conſummation per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; As before in the eight chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. VVhere heate is multiplied, It is indifferent to congeale earth and melt waxe, to rarifie water into ayre, or incinerate Combuſtible mater. Clay in the potters hand, and wood in the grauers, are in the workemans pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to forme at his pleaſure, Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to all ſhapes: So is the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe in the minde of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14570:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>But after one forme induced there is no place for any other without deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt. So Nature (though not abridged, and ſo ſhort tyed as mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme) before the ſpecificall perfection of any thing, is free to any thing. For things perfected haue attained the laſt determinate end of their poſsibility, and therein naturall motion tending to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration doth ceaſe: But the ſeedes and ſpermatical ſubſtances haue not attained any end or perfection, neither be out of thelatitude of indetermination, &amp; indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſſe; and therfore are in the power of the predominant cauſes to produce ſuch effects, as anſwere them: which be moſt vniuerſall, moſt generall, ſuch as before are ſpoken of and declared. This in any forme meerely artificiall cannot be; becauſe the matter in which art wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hath no internall cauſe actiue, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther power nor appetite naturall to the effects of art, but lyeth there like a peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patetick priuation: and all reſteth in the braine and hand of the Workman, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and forreine to the matter. It may be obiected, and commonly is, That of any
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14570:25"/>ſeede or ſpermaticall matter nothing can naturally bee produced or bred; but a body of that kind or ſpecies, of which the ſeed is: and that therefore God in the ſeuerall bleſſings of his ſeuerall creatures commaunded euery one to increaſe and multiply in his owne kinde. But heerein we condemne the ſhallownes of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and beſotted reaſon, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding onely things at hand, and the firſt face, looke no further. Generally any ſeed groweth to a perfection of life, being receiued in any neere matrice of his own next <hi>Genus:</hi> though this thing ſo produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced be not ſpecificall to any kind, either of male or female. And this is of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall power of cauſes ſubalternately ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. But this is againſt the end of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificall nature, euer intending the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the ſpecies, and ſo the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things like in ſpecie, that may haue the like power of propagation in their owne kind, which is not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the naturall law, but alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the commaundement. So for preſeruation of families the Iewes had a commaundement in what Tribe and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14570:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtocke to marrie; Yet, if they married contrarie to that commandement, there were children borne. So for chaſtitie and preſeruation of families, adulterie is forbidden; Yet there be whole genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of adulterous mixture, according to the naturall gift, though with breach of the morall law. The ſeede of man receiued into his proper matrice can na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally produce nothing but man; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in certaine cauſes of <hi>ſuperfetation,</hi> vnequalitie, &amp;c. Yet theſe bee called vnnaturall errours, &amp;c. and ſo they bee, beeing compared to the finall intent. But beeing in the matrice of ſome other Animall there is formed a Monſter, no man. <hi>Partus exparte ſequitur ventrem.</hi> So in all other Animals, elſe we ſhould bee more full of Aſſes, &amp; want Mules. Hence commeth the prouerb, <hi>Africaſemper ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid apportat noui.</hi> The like we ſee in Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, both in grafts &amp; ſeedes: which for the moſt part are in the hands of the husbandman, and gardener, to alter at their pleaſure. For, as it is true that nature doth produce ſeede and ſpermaticall ſubſtances, ſo it is moſt certaine that the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14570:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>hand of man may ioyne them together in any other matrice then that by which they are ſpecificated: or, if they be her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maphroditicall, plant them in like ſort in any other matrice: And beeing ſo ioyned or planted, nature will fall to worke, and neuer ceaſe vntill ſhee haue brought the matter to the laſt perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on poſſible for thoſe cauſes to induce, bee it more or leſſe excellent, then the ſpecies of the ſeede. Inſtance of this is not ſo eaſily giuen in minerals: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their ſpermaticall matter is not ſo familiar amongſt vs. Yet a man paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in ſearch, diligent in obſeruing, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious in reading, induſtrious in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, may ſatisfie himſelfe therein. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things bee fartheſt from ſenſe, and therefore more difficult. In the creation there is no mention made of Minerals: But they bee afterwards named for the riches of ſome of the countries diuided by the riuers flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Eden. And in the whole Scriptures verie little is taught of their originall, and that verie darkely.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14570:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> This is the chiefe ſweate and labour wherein man eateth his naturall bread. It is ſomwhere ſaid, <hi>Out of much earth is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a little gold.</hi> But if wee can finde out their material element, it will be no hard matter to know their next ſeedie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>All things that are of the earth ſhall turne to earth againe,
<note place="margin">Ecleſ. 40.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and they that are of the waters ſhall returne into the ſea.</hi> In <hi>Iob</hi> it is briefly toucht, yet more plainly then els<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in one continued place. <hi>The dead things are formed vnder the waters,
<note place="margin">Job. 26.5.</note> or neere vnto them.</hi> This ſheweth truely the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall element of the pureſt minerals.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 8.1.</note> And againe, <hi>The ſiluer hath his veine, and the gold his place where they take it. Iron is taken out of the duſt, and braſſe is moulten out of the ſtone. God putteth an end to darkneſſe, and hee trieth the perfection of all things. He ſetteth a bound of darkeneſſe and of the ſhadow of death. The floud breaketh out againſt the inhabitant, and the waters forgotten of the foote, being higher then man, are gone away. The ſtones thereof are a place of ſaphires, and the duſt of it is gold. There is a path which no fowle hath knowne, neither hath the Kytes eyeſeene: the Lyons whelpes haue not walked it, neither the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14570:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lions paſſed thereby. Hee putteth his handes vpon the rockes, and his eye ſeeth euerie preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing. He bindeth the flouds, that they doe not ouerflow, and the thing that is hid bringeth to light. But where is wiſedome found, and where is vnderſtanding? &amp;c.</hi> Not propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the diuine application and ſenſe of this place, conſider as a chimicall natural Philoſopher in theſe verſes, what is ment by <hi>dead things, waters, veine, place, darkneſſe, ſhaddow of death, floud, inhabitant, bread, fire turned vp, duſt, vnknowne path, Kites eye, Lions whelpe, Lyon, Rockes, Mountaines,</hi> and then you may boaſt that you know the beginnings, ſpermaticall ſubſtance and true generation of mettals. And for your better helpe in this ſearch take with you one thing out of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> &amp; beleeue it as an article of your naturall creede. <hi>Heate is life, and cold is cauſe of death. The effect of heate and life is openneſſe of the body and fluidnes; congelation and immobilitie is of cold and death. Whatſoeuer tinckteth into a white colour, hath the nature of life and the property of light, and power cauſing life; on the other ſide, whatſoeuer tinkteth into blackneſſe, or maketh blacke, communicateth in nature
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14570:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>with death, and hath the nature of darkeneſſe, and power to kill. The coagulation and fixation of this corruption is the earth with his coldnes. The houſe is euer dead, but that which dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth therein liueth.</hi> But to proceede in our intent: wee ſeeke not to make or haue produced, by nature ſingle, or helped by the hand of her ſeruant art, any ſuch irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular monſter as is contrarie to any law or commandement in the aſſertion of vnitie, or againſt the naturall and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced chaſtitie of naturall ſpecifications, as by the iſſue ſhall appeare. We ſearch a ſubſtance of naturall equalitie of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, exalted in Hermaphroditicall fruitfulneſſe of it ſelfe, aboue the three forenamed kindes, that it may bee to euery of them generally applicable, and with their indiuiduals be made ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call to all, and each; wherein wee offer no vnhallowed violence to any thing. And therefore wee ſay, As it is not perpetually neceſſarie that the thing produced muſt euer anſwer the kinde of that whoſe ſeede it was, but may be and often is traduced particularly as is ſaid: So alſo is it as infalliblie true, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14570:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a ſpermaticall matter may bee made naturally, a tranſcendent vniuerſall and generall ſubſtance, <hi>Genus generum</hi> and <hi>Forma formarum,</hi> of ſuch propertie, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and efficacie as hath beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. And this reſteth for vs further to prooue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 11.</head>
               <p>IN euery of the three kinds, whereof wee ſpeake, <hi>Animals, Vegetables,</hi> and <hi>Minerals,</hi> this thing muſt bee ſought. But we muſt reſolue of the neereſt. It is eaſier for nature to make aire of water, then of earth. And the caruer chooſeth not the whole truncke to make his ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but a peece of timber fit and readie ſquared, where there is no ſuperfluitie, but that which filles vp the hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which hee is to engraue: No defect but of the forme, which hee muſt make, &amp;c. In each of theſe three kindes there bee conſiderable, The whole entire or integrall perfected in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuidualles, Their partes, Their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14570:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>excrements, their ſpermes and ſpermaticall ſubſtance. Againſt all which Nature in this work doth wholly except, ſauing onely ſperme or ſpermaticall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The whole body is concluded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the confluence of ſpecification: and Nature hath therein done all that ſhe intended; and ſo motion ceaſeth, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid in the next precedent Chapter. The like reaſon is of partes; In excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments many haue either beene mired, or drowned altogether, with what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe themſelues beſt know, with what reaſon other men can iudge, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer taught by ill ſauoured experience. The elementall proportion of euery thing is knowne onely to Nature, not to man. Wee muſt neither part nor ioyne, but continue the application of Natures inſtruments, vntill all the Elements ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to our ſight cleane, in or vnder one Element. For then hath Nature in that one Element weighed and meaſured all the Elements, whereby their ſpecificall Nature is wholly changed from that which it firſt was into a generall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. If the foundation of this building
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14570:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>bee laide vpon offals and excrements, which haue no vſe but for the draft, and cannot bee handled without offence of nature, nor ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of without a Preface of reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; ſurely we are incloſed in an il fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored ſtraight. That which is vnfit for noriſhment of others, vnwholſom to the body wherein it is conteined, intended of Nature to no other vſe, but that which it hath already attained, excrementiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous not onely to the body from whence by excretion it is caſt, but euen in it ſelfe in temperament and digeſtion, ſhall ſuch a ſcorne of all things bee the cheefe flower in Natures Garland, or beare the key of her treaſury? What though ſuch a matter bee full of ſtrong ſpirits, able to poyſon a man, or choak a dogge? that vrgeth nothing; for we hope to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders of great wonders without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, or need of much water to waſh. Nature loues cleanlineſſe; becauſe God hath made nothing profitable for man, to the attaining whereof he ſhal be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to any diſhoneſt or vnſeemely thing. It importeth not what conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bee made in this behalfe from the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14570:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhadowes of good Writers, nor what Orator this opinion hath: he teacheth nothing but the old repentance of yong men. Beleeue him not though he haue fiue hundred on his ſide. So for vs there is nothing left but the ſeminall matter, in ſome of the three kindes. For the more ſimple the compoſition of any thing is, the neerer it is to the firſt cauſes, and communicateth more aboundantly with the generall beginnings of all things; becauſe ſubalternate cauſes, authors of ſpecificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be fewer. But the ſperme or ſeede of euery thing, Animal, Vegetable, Mineral, is more ſimple in compoſition, and tyed with fewer ſubalternate cauſes of ſpecification, then the body or perfect indiuiduall, whoſe ſeed it is. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery ſeede is neerer the firſt cauſes, and communicateth more abundantly with the generall beginning, &amp;c. And of ſuch a ſubſtance Nature may make that generall compound we ſeeke after. But for better declaration heereof, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of matrices or wombs are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be vnderſtood. And the manners of the ſeedes growing and increaſing in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14570:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>euery of them, ſo much as concerneth this preſent purpoſe: whereof I haue more amply written in the <hi>Poſſible Perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Miſcibles,</hi> and in the <hi>Poſſibility of Naturall Tranſmutations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 12.</head>
               <p>ANimals haue apparently male and female diſtinct in ſeuerall bodies (vnderſtand them of perfection, and for the moſt part of vniuocall generation) And therfore diſtinct or ſeueral ſpermes: which being mixed in their proper ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice, grow vp to perfection in their own kinde, as God hath appointed. The ſeede onely is prolificall and matter of birth: The matrice is but the place, or, as you would ſay, the houſe and Tenement ordeined for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and breeding thereof, vnto ſuch a particular end. And becauſe euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thing in this kinde is farre greater then the ſeede of which it came, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice muſt haue amongſt other faculties, this one eſpecially, <hi>To nouriſh.</hi> In men, <hi>quadrupedes,</hi> &amp; rauenous fiſhes in the ſeas,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14570:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>Whales, Swordfiſhes, Whirlepooles, Thornpooles, Sharkes, Porkpiſces, Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhes, and ſome Amphibials, as Seales, Sea-calues, Sea-horſes, &amp;c.) they be all nouriſhed within the body of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or female, where they be conceiued, though not all alike. In Men and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drupedes, there be certaine conducts &amp; veines in the Matrice for that purpoſe. And this nouriſhment is of that which the mother or female parent receiueth &amp; digeſteth: and for want therof, the birth ſeldom cometh to perfection, or at leaſt is vnnaturally wretched; ſo likewiſe in ſome Amphibials. In the Fiſhes whereof we ſpeake it is not ſo. For their young, being neuer aboue two at one birth, haue growing from the midſt of their nauell, (or that which to them is in ſtead of a nauell) a white pipe or veine like a nauell ſtring, broad at the bottome, full of a thicke milky ſubſtance, whereof it may be thought they be nouriſhed vntill they be ſpawned; other Fiſhes and Fowles be (concerning this) in another difference: For Fiſhes, either they firſt breede their Egges, and keepe them continually in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14570:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>their bodies, till they bee deliuered of a young perfect Fiſh; as Thornebackes, and ſuch other cartilagineous or griſtly fiſhes: or they breed Egges, and after lay them in a hole made vpon the land in a ſandy ground, which bee there hatched with the helpe of heate of the Sunne and Sand: from whence they creepe directly to the Sea; ſuch bee Torteiſes and their kinds: Or they keepe their Egges about them in the rough places vnder their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and about their feete, as Lobſters, Shrimps, Prawnes, Crafiſhes, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be perfected in ſhelles. As Lobſters bee firſt Welkes, and in that ſhell by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees perfected into their kind, &amp; Crabs ſometimes in Oyſters. But whether this be Catholike and of Canonicall perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity, I thinke no man hath beene in all places ſo general a Mermaid, or conſtant Vrinator as to affirme. Or laſtly they breede within themſelues vnperfect Egges, which after they caſt into ſome ſcooring or ſpawning place, whither the male followeth, and ſheddeth his ſperme vpon theſe Egges; ſo they increaſe, grow great, and breed young fiſhes: ſuch be all
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14570:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>kinde of fiſhes not before ſpoken of. And where ſome exclude Torteſes and their kinds from the generation of fiſhes, it is not materiall whether truly or not, for it is all one to our end, which here onely ſearch the difference of matrices, and of the ſeedes growing to ſpecificall perfection. And within theſe differences be all kinds of ſerpents. Now for fowles (we except onely to vs knowne the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe night-bird) the Bat or Rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſe, which layeth no egges, but bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and giueth ſuck as other mice doe, their breed and ſpecificall increaſe is by egges: The male proiecteth his ſperme into the matrice of the female, whoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is not to bring forth a perfect bird, but an egge; which egge ſupplieth the office of a matrice. For it hath in it ſelfe both ſeedes, maſculine and feminine, by the naturall appetite of the Coition of the male and female, before the prolifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call egge be formed: Alſo ſufficient mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of nouriſhment, vntill the bird be hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. In which egge the naturall and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall heate of the maleſeede is ſenſible to the tippe of a mans tonge on the outſide
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14570:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the ſhell, as they know which ſteale Hawkes egges out of the eyrie. In Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles euery Hearbe and Plant is Herma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroditical, being both male and female it ſelfe, concerning propagation. Their naturall propagation is of two ſorts, by ſeede, and by ſlip: for graffes increaſe in the ſame kind, &amp; for the ſame reaſons that ſlips do. The ſeed is from one &amp; the ſelfe ſame plant, made, ripened, and caſt off: it receiueth no help of any other, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſeminarily both fexes in one bodie, and being put into fit ground in ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ayre &amp; time, it riſeth vp and groweth into a new plant or hearb like to that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which it came. The coats or skins where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is cloſed, differ not in vſe much from the skins about the eg: the earth ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the wants which the ſeede hath in it ſelf to increaſe ſpecifically, that is, heat &amp; noriſhment. For without heat there is no attraction, without attraction no noriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And becauſe it is neceſſary that the ſeed increaſe in quantity &amp; greatnes before it becom a plant, attraction of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is neceſſary for euery ſeed: which by the other naturall faculties is altered
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14570:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſpecificated into the ſubſtance of the plant. The like manner of growing and increaſing is in ſlippes and graffes.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Terminus à quo,</hi> the point from whence they proceede, is not ſo remote from compoſition, nor ſo neere to ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie as in ſeedes; which alſo is one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the increaſe in ſlips and graffes is quicker then in feedes. For their attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue vertue and aſſimilation of the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment is ſtronger, &amp;c. In theſe two kinds of Animales and Vegetables (for ſo much as concerneth the preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) we finde the firſt difference of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices to be of two ſorts; <hi>Inſeparable, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi> Then againe of two ſorts, <hi>The ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall bodie of the ſeede prepareth nouriſhment for the increaſe, or that nouriſhment is drawne out of another bodie.</hi> The third difference is alſo of two ſorts, <hi>The heate moouing to gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is either proper to the particular female bodie whoſe ſeede it is, or indifferent to others.</hi> There is alſo a fourth difference, <hi>The nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment attracted in the immediate matrice either is ſpecifically prepared for the ſeede, or is not, but common to all the next genus:</hi> As the moiſture minerall of earth to plants. In
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14570:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſeede there is alſo a difference. <hi>The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuiduall at his firſt birth is greater then the ſeede and ſpermaticall matter was, or not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> for that which is properly called <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men prolificum,</hi> the ſeede powerfull to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is not the whole body of the ſpermaticall matter, but as it were the center thereof: As in egges may eaſily in ſome neereneſſe be ſhowne to the eye, and hereupon lyeth the demonſtration of hereditary diſeaſes, and many other ſtrange thinges in Nature, bred of this ſpermaticall ſuperfluity. The ſumme of theſe two kinds briefly is this.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Thoſe things which haue male and female diſtinct in ſeueral bodies, hauing a naturall appetite each to other, cannot increaſe or multiply their owne kinde without locall motion and actuall copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: whereby both ſeeds, may be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Such be Men, <hi>Quadrupedes,</hi> Fowles, Serpents, Fiſhes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Thoſe things which being brought foorth, bee greater in quantity then the feede or ſpermaticall matter of which they came, muſt haue their ſeede recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into ſuch a matrice from whence
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14570:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14570:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14570:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>they may draw ſufficient nouriſhment, as in men, <hi>quadrupedes,</hi> ſome fiſh, plants.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thoſe things which cannot haue nouriſhment fitly prepared for them to attract, but within the body into whoſe matrice they are receiued; may neuer be ſeparated from thence vntill the time of perfection, and their deliuery; as in men, beaſts, rauenous fiſhes aforeſaid, the Bat onely amongſt thoſe that flye.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Thoſe ſeedes which may by nature be incloſed in a conuenient matrice with apt &amp; ſufficient matter for nouriſhment, vntil the perfection of the birth, may be ſeparated from the body of the female, hauing receiued the maſculine ſeede in a ſeparable matrice, and may bee ripened either by the heate of the ſame body, or of any other naturall or artificiall, being like and equally temperate, as in Egs of Fowles, and ſome Aquatiles.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Thoſe things which being inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a naturall ſeparable matrice, haue not there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſufficient matter for nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, muſt be ſowed or planted in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matrice, which ſhall ſupply this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; as in plants, &amp;c. But herein is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing further to be conſidered more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14570:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the Animall kind, ſpeciallie betweene Man and <hi>Quadrupedes</hi> on the one ſide, &amp; Birds or Foules on the other. The Eg hath a hard ſhell without, a thin skin or membrane within that, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more thin &amp; ſubtile about the yelk, couering and exactly winding about the true prolificall ſeeds of male and female in the ſpermaticall matter; whereby though the outward ſhell were taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, yet the outward ayre cannot imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie touch the true ſeede, neither the aetherious ſpirit preſently vaniſh. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore age or moyſture haue reſolued the very ſperme it ſelf within the eg, whether of both together, or of the ſolitary femals eg, it neuer putrifieth. And for the ſame reaſon the eg with both ſpermes reſiſteth putrefaction longer then the ſole female. And, as is ſaid of thoſe skins defending the ſperme within the Eg, nature in like ſort hath ordained in man, a wombe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condines, &amp;c. not vnlike the defence of the brain in the skull, and 2. meninges, or me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>branes, cald <hi>Dura mater</hi> &amp; <hi>Pia mater:</hi> it being the moſt ſpermaticall ſubſtance in al the body. But in men &amp; <hi>quadrupedes,</hi> thogh it wer poſſible to receiue their ſeed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14570:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>into another matrice, or ſeparable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiner, and to adminiſter heate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto conuenient (as may bee done in egges) yet becauſe that ſeed and ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall matter hath not within it ſelfe ſufficient matter of nouriſhment, but is compelled to attract from the daily nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of the mother: and though this be ſuppoſed poſſible to be ſupplyed, yet the nouriſhment muſt be firſt dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and ſpecificated, for that ſeed by the proper and naturall mother; therefore it were altogether impoſſible that any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall birth ſhould be had thereof. And moreouer this kind of ſeed hath nothing to defend it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the immediate touch of the outward aire, nor to preſerue the vital archaeical ſpirit in the ſeed, that it preſent lie vaniſh not, and leaue the body like a common excrement vnprofitable. Elſe had Nature without cauſe made the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of thoſe ſeeds ſo cloſe, and in a matrice ſo vnſeparable from the female body. Which ſhewes the vanity of the Authours of the bathing conceptions; and deſtroyes their magneticall power of the matrices attraction. All theſe <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:14570:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnderſtood very well, as in many places he hath ſhewed. Wherefore they doe him the more wrong, and haue been little exerciſed in contemplation of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities, that traduce his <hi>Homunculus</hi> or Dwarfe, to any vnſeemly or wicked prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. Now reſteth the third kinde of our diuiſion, that is Minerals: which differeth mainely from Animals, and agreeth very little with Vegetables. Their ſeede is hermaphroditicall, and that into which the ſpecifical forme of minerality in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kind is immediatly brought. By im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly I meane, as in the ſeed of man: we ſay the forme of man is immediatlie brought; That is, man is the laſt forme which Nature intendeth in that ſeede, and the onely ſpecifical forme of which that ſeede is naturally capable. In this kinde there is to bee obſerued ſpecially the difference betweene it and the other two. For in plants with the firſt perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Species</hi> out of the ſeede, which is in the firſt germination of the greene leafe from the root, the <hi>Species</hi> is perfecte but the indiuiduall body is yet weake, tender, and vnperfect, for the ſpecificall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14570:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>vſes of his kind. So in Animals, the <hi>ſpecies</hi> is perfected with the firſt reception of the ſpecificall <hi>forme:</hi> more notably in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acception, in parturition, or enixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: But the indiuidual body requireth time to grow vp to the fulneſſe of his naturall faculties and functions, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the moſt naturall, which is to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply in his owne kind. In Minerals it is not ſo; for as ſoone as they be perfected in their indiuidualitie vnder any <hi>Species</hi> of that kind, they be in the ſame inſtant as powerfull in all dower of their natural vertues, to all vſes whatſoeuer, as if they had bin exiſtently perfected 10000. ages. And of them, thoſe that be multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, be in the ſame inſtant as powerfull as any other. For the whole bodie in the homogeneall matter is all ſeede: and is not increaſed by attraction, but by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, &amp;c. And generallie the neerer any thing commeth, in the naturall compoſition of his ſpecificall indiuidua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, to the ſimplicitie of the Elements, the ſooner after the firſt perfection it is in the full vigor, for the vſe of al vertues, endowments, and faculties of his <hi>ſpecies;</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14570:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>and contrarie. Which is one reaſon that ſome animals be generatiue ſooner then others: and a good paradoxall ground for the difference of ſenſible ſoules, and the degrees of their more or leſſe propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to reaſon &amp; intellect. The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is very profitable in the whole Chimicall Academie. For in thoſe things, which being compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded are moſt homogeneall, and ſtand in the firſt or neereſt approximation to the ſimplicity of the firſt ſymbolizing bodies, the whole ſubſtance in his open body, is totallie or very neere, all ſeed, regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into a bodie generable and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. The myſterie of which ſchoole if any bee curious to vnderſtand, let them reade good Philoſophers. For certainely more then one haue delt liberally here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And in reading let them diligentlie obſerue and collect, whether ſuch ſeede in Metals and other Minerals be pure, or mingled with ſpermaticall ſuperfluity, as is ſaid of the other two kinds. 2. Next whether it be to be gotten onely in the earth before the mettall perfected, or lie hid alſo in the complete body, and may be found by art in diſſolution, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14570:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>regreſſe from compoſition to ſimplicity. 3. And if ſo, then whether it be ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſubſtance by deciſion, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes naturall or artificiall to bee ſeparated from it, or els onely a power in it ſelfe intenſiuely to receiue exaltation, and thereby enabled to giue out of this exuberance vnto others the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his firſt ſpecifical degree. 4. Whether this ſeminarie ſubiect be alike pure and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneall in the totall and ſeparated ſubſtances of euery metalline bodie. Theſe things beeing thus deliuered and vnderſtood; that which remaineth in the neceſſarie demonſtration of this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſubſtance will bee plaine without any difficultie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 13.</head>
               <p>THe inſtruments of nature in bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; procreation are the effects of Spirit, In number three: <hi>Motion, Heat, Light.</hi> And that which we moſt looke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is <hi>Heate,</hi> which neuer is nor can be in any naturall ſubiect without the other 2. nor any of them without the reſt. <hi>Vbi
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14570:38"/>motus talis, ibi calor talis, &amp; lux talis: Vbi calortalis, ibi motus talis, &amp; lux talis: Vbi lux talis, ibi calor talis, &amp; motus talis. Heate</hi> is of two ſorts: In ward, or naturall, of the ſeede or ſubſtance; the ſecond outward or inſtrumentall of the matrice, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wherein the matrice is, or of that which is in ſtead thereof. By this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward inſtrumentall heate the inward na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall heate is ſtirred to actiuitie, and from the ſleepy power or bability (which onely it had) brought vnto, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in actuall working vntill the effect be perfected. Therefore outward inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall heate muſt be ſo fitted, that it ſerue onely to this exciting of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward naturall heate, in moſt exact degree and proportion. This may be familiarly exemplified in egges; which often are ripened, and out of them birds hatched by diuers manners of heate; Not onely by incubation and ſitting of the ſame hen, or any other of the ſame <hi>ſpecies</hi> whoſe egges they were, but of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fowle, and alſo by any other like heate: be it of ſand, aſhes, &amp;c. being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in equall adaptation. That which
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14570:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>is ſpoken of the heate of mans bodie, as vnder his arme-pits or any other part, is ſenſleſſee for the vncertaintie of temper, with variety, ſatiety, want of meate, and drinke, and ſleepe, and paſſions alters the heate both ſubiectiuely and in degree, almoſt euery mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Beſides the ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie perſpiration paſſeth the ſhell, and cauſeth putrefaction. Nature hath giuen vs the firſt experiments of this reaſon: as in the Amphibials before ſpoken of:
<note place="margin">Iob 39.17.</note> and in the <hi>Oſtrich, which leaueth her egges in the earth and maketh them hot in the duſt, &amp; forgetteth that the foot might ſcatter them, or that the wilde beaſts might breake them: he ſheweth himſelfe cruell vnto his yong ones, as they were not his, and is without feare, as if he trauailed in vaine, &amp;c.</hi> Too much heate roaſteth, whereby the ſpirit of life in the ſeede is deſtroied, and the ſubſtance is as it were vitrificat. Too litle heat makes no perfect mixture of the agents &amp; patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; &amp; produceth no reciprocal actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby the work begun proceedeth not, but the matter rots, &amp; the ſpirits de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay. A diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued heat breaketh off na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures worke, ſo that the naturall heat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14570:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>to work in the ſeed to propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dieth in it ſelfe, &amp; can neuer be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe, becauſe the ſpirit of life in the ſame ſeede alſo dieth: And ſo the matter being of eaſie mixture and compoſition putrifieth, without life or power of life, to an vnprofitable end. But it is not ſo in the things of ſtronger mixture &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being neerer to the ſimplicity of the firſt materialities of bodies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And therefore not ſo eaſily ſubiect to deſtractiue putrefaction. Becauſe their very corporal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pounding parts be ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolizing neere the degree of the prime ſymbolizing bodies, not altered out of the circle &amp; latitude of the <hi>ſpecies</hi> digeſted or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cocted; except there be addition of ſomething extraneall in the mixture. For then the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pound co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification yeeldeth to the predominance of the virtuall predominant in the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Yet ſtill is preſerued within the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination &amp; general eſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the next immediate <hi>genus</hi> of that <hi>ſpecies;</hi> not excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that circle or latitude, except it be directed to our known period of vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality. The matrice being open or not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14570:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>perfectly cloſed, the ſpirit of life with his heate and light of life, flyeth away vnto the Catholike fountaine of all naturall ſpirits, <hi>Heate</hi> and <hi>Light:</hi> and ſo leaueth the matter dead: as in Mines of mettals, if there be any vent or paſſage by which the mineral ſpirit may vapour out or flie, that neuer cometh to perfection, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall obiections be made againſt this, but none grounded on reaſon, <hi>A radice mineralitatis metallicae.</hi> An open ſtomacke neuer digeſteth well. But herein is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence obſeruable betweene Animals, Vegetables and Minerals. For in Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals the ſeedes and ſpermes doe vtterly periſh, nay euen the formed Embryons by the opennes of the matrice; and the formed chickens in the egge either by diſcontinuing the heate, or a little cracke in the ſhell.</p>
               <p>Of Vegetables we ſee ſeedes lying on the face of the earth on ſtones and wals to ſhoot their rootes, ſtalkes, burgeons and leaues, which die afterwards for want of nouriſhment, after they haue ſpent in corporall augment that natural humidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and nutritiue ſubſtance which the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14570:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeed in his ſeparable matrice conteined. But in Minerals wee finde, that though ſome part of the matter exhale and flye through the opennes of the matrice, yet that which remaineth may bee brought afterwards to his full ſpecificall perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on if the matrice be cloſed againe. And this is a good and obſerueable ground to inueſtigate the true ſeede of all mettalles, the manner of ripening them, their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, regeneration, and exuberation: Alſo to confirme the doctrine of homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneitie of that which is moſt perfect in the metalline predicament: alſo of the ſymbolizing of the corporall metalline Elements before ſpoken of. Being vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it is a key opening the doore of many myſtical veſtries in <hi>Hermes</hi> temple. And ſo wee ſee, that it is impoſſible for any thing to attaine naturall perfection more then it hath, without naturall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch as nature vſeth in generation &amp; augmentation: Therefore in all times and in all matters the cautions heere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered muſt be carefully obſerued. That the ſeede may bee brought to ſuch moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and enabled to receiue the benefit of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14570:41"/>ſuch naturall exaltation. The reaſons &amp; cauſes why euery thing is particularized in his birth are two. The firſt, becauſe it is kept and bred vp in a matrice where it is fed and nouriſhed with nouriſhment by a ſpecificated bodie, which in things not hermaphroditicall wee may prooue true by monſters begotten betweene male and female ſpecifically differing. The ſecond, becauſe the feede and ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall matter is ſo ſtraightly encloſed in the matrice, that the elements cannot bee enlarged to any vnbridled circulare motion by which onely is acquired that laſt excellent perfection of which wee ſpeake. One probable argument of this is, that minerals bee more generall and powerfull in effect then either Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Animals, or any other ſuperterrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als: And the heauens more then they. For the Elements ſo communicate in their ſymbolicall qualities, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe ro worke each on other. The earth ſtriuing to ouercome and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute the water, and to bring the fire in accord therewith; likewiſe the ayre, with the water and fire, water with earth and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14570:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>aire, fire with aire and earth, And finally all with all to make one, &amp;c: and if it happen the combate of Elements: to be in a matter, hauing the properties of life before ſpoken of (though it liue in a dead houſe,) and that in a matrice or recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, where they cannot be diſperſed, nor the ſpirits flie out, Their Ambition of victorie and tranſmutation muſt needs end at laſt and determine in ſome natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall compounded bodie which ſhall not be ſpecificated to any kinde, Animall, Vegetable, or Minerall. But that in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication it may be aboue them all, ſuch as this generalitie of matter muſt needs produce. For where the matter is the moſt ſimple &amp; pure mixture of Eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, indefinite, indeterminate, and this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter continued in naturall motion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſperſing the elements or ſpirits, without any adition of other matter, It is impoſſible that the action of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue and paſſion of the paſſiue ſhould euer ceaſe, ſo long as the cauſes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, that is any inequalitie in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of theſe elements. By which meanes there muſt needs be produced a bodie of moſt exact and abſolute tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14570:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>wherein no element is predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: ſuch is the ninth temperament of which <hi>Galen</hi> ſpeaketh, and of late writers is called the temperament of iuſtice: which they denie not to be at ſome time really in ſome Man; but allow it not to continue any time, becauſe of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany alteration, which that bodie ſuffereth, by reaſon of the triangular ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification. If therefore they will grant this in ſuch a market of meates and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, as man is, why may wee not boldly require it much more in ſuch a bodie as we ſpeake of? which hauing gotten his perfection in the fire by the naturall triumph of all elements in a quinteſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall bodie, muſt needs hold this exact temperament and the dowers thereof inuiolably againſt all elementall forces. For if this exact meaſure of digeſtion bee compleate in a ſubſtance not yet reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the latitude and indifferencie betweene generall and ſpecificall; the cauſe of ſuch momentany alteration is taken away: eſpecially if in the choiſe of the roote; the number of the angles bee anſwerable. And then it muſt needs bee
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14570:42"/>reduced vnto, and reſt in an homogene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſubſtance of moſt perfect naturall vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: more permanent in being, and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ouer all elements, then any mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, euen gold it ſelfe, remaining in his metalleitie. In which worke the thing produced exceedes not in quantie, the firſt ſpermaticall ſubſtance, becauſe there is no attraction of nouriſhment: But the moiſt is foode to the drie, the cold to the hot, the dry to the moiſt, and hot to the cold. So they change and are changed, vntill they bee all in equall ſtrength and proportion geometrically anatiſed, inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably vnited in one body. And before the matter comes to this point it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer properly ſaid to be <hi>one,</hi> or <hi>vnitie.</hi> For as a true vnitie ſuffereth no diuiſion, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in deſcending into fractions, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending to warring dualitie; ſo this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance beeing more tranſcendent then any naturall ſubſtance of Ariſtotles predicament, and hauing no heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall parts of different compoſition, mixture, and temper, neither any noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch difference, is and muſt needs be the moſt perfect abſolute vnitie of all
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14570:43"/>naturall ſublunare compounds. The like whereof nature alone and of her ſelfe could neuer produce, being hindred by the foreſaid cauſes of ſpecificall definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but requireth the band of Gods i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and then is able of her ſelfe to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that, which before ſhee could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapt. For man being ſo much aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by how much hee is more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers illumined and formally eſſenſifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of a diuine intellect, doth in many things helpe nature to proceede natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally farther by many degrees, then ſhee could without that helpe, and ſo in the excellence of nature either exceedeth, or greatly inricheth nature in the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of naturall effects. But whether na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone hath produced and left inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in any naturall bodie this myſticall tranſcendent, and reall exiſting predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is a great queſtion. Doubtleſſe ſhee hath in a certaine number, and maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnder a definition of determinate vſes in the philoſophie of generations. But ſhe hath not, neither euer ſhall <hi>per ſe,</hi> without the help of our ſcience and art, act and produce it in the number which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14570:43"/>we admire; nor vnmasked in the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous triumph ouer Animals, Vegetables, and Minerals, beeing in a high freedome of generalitie, indifferent to all, <hi>Genus ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerum</hi> and <hi>Forma formarum naturalium.</hi> And ſo we may truly ſay, that this matter whereof wee ſpeake (at which ſo many good Archers haue bent their bowes) is a naturall thing brought forth in his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled glorie by the helpe of art; yet is it, neither naturall nor artificiall, but hath a nature and eſſence, exceeding common capacitie: And to know in what forme or bodie this ſtrange ſonne of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall ariſe, and in what attire hee ſhall be preſented to the world at his firſt natiuitie, wee muſt conſider the ſpheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſcale or ladder of naturall things: wherein wee ſhall finde an admirable beautie and proportion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> laſt of which ſphere being Man, a reaſonable Creature, ſtandeth in place and nature next vnto ſpirits: and they both next vnder God tranſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aboue the ſphere of Creatures. Betweene theſe two we finde things in deſcent leſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then ſpirits, more noble and perfect
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14570:44"/>then Man, concerning his elementall dowry, and durability of his body. In aſcent leſſe noble then Man, concerning that forme whereby hee is called Man, and a fellow ſeruant with ſpirits, more noble then the ſpirits concerning their immediate application to natural things for perfection. Theſe bee the heauens with all their parts and diſtinctions: the Elements, Minerall, Plantall, Animall: whereby it plainly appeareth that thoſe things whoſe vſe is moſt generall to the perfection before ſpoken, of elementall naturall bodies, are fartheſt from the ſimplicity of ſpirits: But thoſe things which be fartheſt from the ſimplicity of ſpirits, haue in their naturall being leaſt ſhew and apparence of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of ſpirit. And where the effects of ſpirit in thenaturall body be moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that body is in the ſphere remoued by moſt differences and ſpecifications from the Elements. So is Plantall farther then Minerall, and Animal then Plantal: and in the Animal kind, though humane agree with the reſt, as hauing the natural life in blood, yet it goeth one degree
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14570:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>further by that ſparke of diuine irradia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which it is eſſentially formed with an immortall ſubſtance; which though diuerſlie traducible and paſſiue by the naturall part of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon <hi>Genus</hi> in the Organs whereof it worketh, yet either in real or conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>platiue ſequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on comprehendeth Notions of al diuine and immortall things, and ſo verily find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelfe in the rancke of immortall eſſences, and ſpirituall lifes. This thing therefore we ſpeake of, being the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Elements in euery elementarie body, and made with reſt and peace purchaſed with the warre of his owne vnmingled, vndiſperſed, vndefiled Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, muſt needs be the meane or cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this ſphere, the firſt compound vnder heauen hauing no proper name of his owne to vs knowne: yet neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appearing in that ſhape which the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their firſt compoſition, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by the ſpecificating cauſes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid muſt needes produce. That is <hi>Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale fluidum:</hi> this is <hi>Aqua viſcoſa, Aquae permanens,</hi> and the Philoſophers <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> ſought of many, found of few. The
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14570:45"/>paſſage of all naturall cauſes of this birth, <hi>Raymond Lullie</hi> well vnderſtood in the firſt Booke of his Teſtament, being of <hi>Theorie,</hi> in the figure proceeding from Elements to Mettals, and from Mettals to Elements, by eight letters: <hi>A.B.C.D. E.F.G.H.</hi> which we haue therefore here ſet downe; wherein we giue but this one note, that it is a matter of deepe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, how <hi>G.</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> be immediate, that is, <hi>Sulphur Aqueum</hi> and <hi>Metalla,</hi> for it conteineth a great practicke myſtery.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>This heptagonall is in all naturall ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations truly circular.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:14570:45"/>
               <p> The ſcale of degrees and differences in deſcent and aſcent, of which we ſpeak, here followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>Scala Magica naturalis.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Deus</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Potestas</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">
                           <hi>Voluntas</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Spiritus</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell rows="10">Syntheſis</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Materia</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Animal</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rows="10">Analyſis</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Angeli</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Rationale</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Coelum diuiſor</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Animalia.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Caelum ſtellatum</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Plantae</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Elementa</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Minerae</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Minerae</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Elementa</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Plantae</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Coelum ſtellatum</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Animalia</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Coelum diuiſor</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Animal</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Angeli</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Rationale.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Materia.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 14.</head>
               <p>FOr our better vnderſtanding herein, let vs conſider the Hiſtorie of the Creation, <hi>That there be two waters; ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, inferior; Two earths, Eden, and therest
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14570:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>without and about it: Two waterings, Coho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation by the miſte aſcending out of the earth without attraction; Another by raine attrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the earth and lower globe by heate; Two Cultures or Manurings, naturall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of man, and artificiall by the help of Man.</hi> The waters being ſpiritualized, and hauing receiued motion, light and heat, were parted into ſuperiour, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior. The inferior as connaturall to the ſuperior, and of the ſame wombe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with them (though in leſſe meaſure) in this rich birthright.</p>
               <p>The inferior waters being coupled in marriage with their naturall and equall Spouſe the earth, enriched her with fruitfulneſſe, as a meane by God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the Lawe of Nature by him created and eſtabliſhed. And of all the earth that Sanctuary of Gods Image and glorie, the Garden <hi>Eden</hi> had the preheminence. This choſen earth was made fruitfull by water of miſte or vapor, aſcending out of it ſelfe, and againe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending vpon it. This miſte the earth did yeeld of her naturall ayre and porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſpirit, and heate conceiued in the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14570:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>vniuerſall coupling, as it were ingende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the Waters in the firſt darknes. The ſecond watering, by raine, God cauſed to beginne after the Starres, and Man were created. It commeth natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by attraction of the Sunne and other Starres, and the violence of windes from the earth, particularized in ſuch ſort as of the Starres, &amp;c. before is ſaide. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the heate of the ſunne is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies alike in any place of the earth, no not in the ſame anniuerſary day, houre, nor ſeaſon; neither the ſunne, &amp;c. alike neere, and aſpected at all times to the ſame place; neither matter vaporous euer in like quantity, quality, and readineſſe to bee attracted: beſide the particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of other Aſtronomicall and Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call obſeruations; therefore the raine is not alwaies in the ſame meaſure, time, and ſeaſon. Hence come vnſeaſonable times in the foure quarters, too hot, or too cold, too wet, or too dry, and ſo in complexion, with impurities of the firſt mixture minerall, new diſeaſes; and much trouble. But where the earth is watered by vapor or miſte begotten in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14570:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>darkneſſe, aſcending from it ſelfe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine deſcending, no ſuch miſchances happen. But Nature reioycing and well pleaſed with her ſelfe, earth and water is made fruitfull vnto perfection. And then the two Cultures or Manurings are both neceſſary, and cannot faile of a good bleſſing: but from Elements ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, become Elements elementate in the firſt mixture ſimply quinteſſentiall, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnate with aethereall nouriſhing, not burning fire: whereof reſulteth this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike vnity, generall in application to all things, which wee ſeeke for and ſo much admire, and ſhall reioyce to haue found. Theſe two Cultures are, the one naturall by Coh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bation; the other artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall by man, attending onely the ſelect earth or Garden to dreſſe and keepe it, not hauing ſwallowed the fruite of dua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, the apple of euil: nor being driuen, or ſelfe-ſtraying out of this Garden into other ground, where not ſuch miſte or vapor doth ariſe; and which is watered with the raine of the time of generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and corruptions. This is that ladder in Nature of Angels aſcending and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14570:47"/>betweene heauen and earth. This is the hoope of pure gold, round, endleſſe, and bottomleſſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed according to the truth and true reſemblance, <hi>Imago ſpei,</hi> the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall wedding ring of theſe two great parents of naturall things. This is the continuall ſpring-tide of neuer vading greennes in the Emerauld, the wealth of <hi>Hermes</hi> his Smaragdine Table, <hi>True with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaſing, moſt true, The ſtrong ſtrength of all (naturall) ſtrength, becauſe it will ouercome euerie ſubtile, and pierce euery ſolid thing, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Cuius vis est Integra, ſi verſa fuerit in terram.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
